<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Independency accused by nine severall arguments: written by a godly learned minister, to a member of Mr. John Goodwins congregation, and acquitted by severall replyes to the said arguments by a member of the same church. In both which, sweetnesse of spirit, and soundnesse of arguments have been endeavoured. Published according to order.</title>
            <author>I. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P53A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E296_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200209</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861014</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861014</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113141</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113141)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E296[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Independency accused by nine severall arguments: written by a godly learned minister, to a member of Mr. John Goodwins congregation, and acquitted by severall replyes to the said arguments by a member of the same church. In both which, sweetnesse of spirit, and soundnesse of arguments have been endeavoured. Published according to order.</title>
                  <author>I. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Overton in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A member of the same church" = I.P., who has signed the work on page [3] and at end.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 12th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregationalism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113141:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Independency accuſed <hi>By nine ſeverall</hi> ARGUMENTS: Written by a godly learned Miniſter, to a Member of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> JOHN GOODWINS CONGREGATION, <hi>AND</hi> Acquitted by ſeverall REPLYES to the ſaid ARGUMENTS by a Member of the ſame CHURCH.</p>
            <p>In both which, ſweetneſſe of ſpirit, and ſoundneſſe of Arguments have been endeavoured.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GALAT. 6.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, yee which are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſſe, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Overton</hi> in <hi>Popes-head Alley</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113141:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113141:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend, my deare and loving Paſtor, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> JOHN GOODWIN,</hi> Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Colemanſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare and reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our favourable acceptance of my preſent pains, and candid conſtruction of enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging my ſelf therein, is my humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt by my preſent addreſſe, whereof, though mine own inſufficiency might beget my ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion; yet the knowledge of your love (which thinketh no evill) gives me ſatisfaction; for although the piety and parts of my ingenious Antagoniſt did challenge an opponent of ſutable endowments; and renders me preſumptuous for my attempt therein, (unworthy to be named in competition with him) yet the perfect knowledge of your preſſing pains of ſeverall kindes in the work of the Lord, ſtopping the mouth, which otherwaies would have begg'd your own labours in this preſent buſineſſe, together with the requeſts of ſome of our friends, preſt mee hereunto, wherin, if I have not prejudiced the Cauſe I plead for; diſtaſted you, nor diſhonoured God, but (though in the leaſt meaſure) have further'd the truth, it is the higheſt ambition, and greateſt reward of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The unworthieſt to be numbred amongst your flock,</hi> J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113141:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nity in judgement amongſt the Saints, is the promiſed bleſſing of another age, but Unity in affection is our preſent duty confeſſed by all, though the practice hereof be the care of few; witneſſe the bitter pens, and railing lines of men profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the feare of God, each againſt his brother, i'th faith, to the ſcandall of Religion, and ſcorne of Profeſſion, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of God, and diſgrace of the Goſpel, the joy of the Jeſuite, and hazard of the kingdome, the ſtumbling of others coming into the paths of life, ſeeing them trac'd with Lions, and Bears, and Wolves, and Tygres, in ſtead of Lambs and Doves, the meek Saints of the moſt high God, as if they had gotten a ſpeciall diſpenſation in this preſent age, to ſlander the perſons, traduce the actions, reproach the names of their deareſt brethren, to fight the Lords battels with the Devils weapons, and to trample under foot that royall Law of their liege Lord, <hi>This is my commandement, that you love one another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 13.33.</note> In this preſent Diſcourſe thou ſhalt not obſerve (allowance afforded to humane frailty) the leaſt tincture of that <hi>unchriſtian</hi> ſtrain, the minde of the Lord, and truth of Chriſt being the mutuall deſigne of my opponent and my ſelf: I have not altered one word of his Letter, only whereas he writ it entire, I have preſented thee with each <hi>Argument,</hi> and immediate <hi>Replies,</hi> with a different character between the one and the other, for thy more diſtinct apprehenſion of both. I ſay no more, but prove, and approve, and the Lord direct thy heart into the knowledge and love of the truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113141:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My deare Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu are not ignorant, how reſpectfull and reverent I have carryed my ſelf towards the <hi>Congregationall Way,</hi> almoſt ever ſince you knew mee, and daily am, both praying and reading, that I may be fully perſwaded in mine own heart whether that, or the other <hi>Way,</hi> called <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Way of God. For this end, I have given my ſelf to the peruſall of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Goodwins</hi> Theomachia, and his juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of it againſt <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Prynne,</hi> and ſo farre as my judgment reaches, he gets the better of him; but yet ſome doubts I have, to which I cannot pick anſwers out of both his books. I dare not be guilty of that which hee ſo much pleads againſt, <hi>blind obedience, implicit faith.</hi> I muſt not take up <hi>Religion</hi> by the lumps (as once <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomas Goodwin</hi> ſaid) I muſt not pin my faith upon the ſleeve of any perſon or perſons upon earth, though never ſo holy or learned, as not knowing whither they may carry it; the beſt of men are but men at beſt: both God and men will expect from me, that I be able to render a Scripturall Reaſon of my faith and conſcience, and therefore I requeſt you earneſtly, to improve your intereſt in ſome friend (you know I have no acquaintance with any Divine of that Way) to communicate their light to mee in the following particulars, and doubtleſſe, it will be an addition to my charitableneſſe towards that Way, if not quite pull me into't; for 'tis my full purpoſe of heart, to ſall down before the truth when I meet it, and know it; I will be their's (what ere come on't) that I find to have not the ſtrangeſt hand, but argument.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſpirit of ſobriety and Chriſtian moderation doth ſo ſweetly look through your lines, caſting ſuch a gracious aſpect of meekneſſe, humility, with all lovely and Chriſtian ingenuity and modeſty, that upon the firſt reading thereof, I deſired to ingage my ſelf into your Chriſtian acquaintance, and to return an anſwer (being deſired hereunto) according to my judgement unto your
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113141:4"/>Letter, being much encouraged by the ſpirit of your writing, which promiſeth mee a candid and an ingenuous interpretation of my mean indeavours, and as the firſt fruits thereof, I ſhall humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire theſe things of you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That you will pleaſe to paſſe by what you obſerve weak, and wanting, (whereof you may find more then enough) and to beſtow your more ſerious conſiderations upon any thing (if ſuch a thing can be found) which you may judge more valid; the pureſt gold may be found in the groſſeſt earth; and arguments for truth are oftentimes like neighbours in their vicinity: the poor, weak, and inſufficient, have the rich, able and more ſufficient for their ſupport and comfort: truth is welcome to a gracious heart, though evidenced but by one or two ſound arguments, when many ſhall ſay, Lo, it is here, or there, and cannot ſhew it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That you would be a Midwife to any argument which you judge pregnant, and which hath truth in the belly thereof, having ſtrength to conceive, but not to bring forth; ſurely the ſons of truth cannot but help the truth in ſtraits, which often ſuffers through the great inſufficiencie of the abettors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; the hearts of the Saints ſometimes can better defend the truth diſcovered then their tongues or pens; a nimble wit, and learned head prove not alwayes the truths friend; but Sir, I do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge you.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That if we cannot agree in <hi>this</hi> truth, yet wee may love one another in <hi>the</hi> truth; let this be written in letters of gold upon the foreheads of all the Saints, <hi>HOLINES TO THE LORD, AND LOVE TO THE BRETHREN:</hi> Faith and Love are the golden pillars, ſupporting the hearts of the Saints together in the ſpirit of which love, I come to your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That no caſe is ſo cleer, but ſome queſtion may be raiſed about it, to which preſent ſatisfaction may not be given; it is ſufficient if the main things things be juſtified.</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT I.</head>
               <p>LEt it be granted that the Churches in the Apoſtles time were <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall,</hi> (for all nationall profeſſion in the world was either
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113141:4"/>
                  <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſh</hi>) yet if they were to be the preſident of the form of Church-ordering and government for ever under the Goſpell, how could all the Churches the Apoſtles had conſtituted up and down the world; yea, and all particular Chriſtians be ſo corrupted, as to ſuffer the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and worſhip of God to be taken from them ſo eaſily, as that none (that I can heare of) are found upon record, to have ſtood up for Chriſt, and the truth, but Nationall-Church-government was brought in? and we cannot learn that there was any ſcuffle on conteſtation againſt it. I do not think there can be named one truth of God that <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or any other <hi>Heretique</hi> fought againſt, but tis poſſible with a little ſearch or ſtudy to name thoſe pe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſons that diſputed, or w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, on ſuffered in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it, and ſtood in the gap to keep out the error, only in this, all the Chriſtian Churches in the world ſuffer'd the government of Chriſt (which is ſo deare to the heart of a Saint) to be deſtroyed, and a falſe <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> government and worſhip to be obtruded on them, and all ſides are ſilent in the buſineſſe; Where is the Scribe? is there no Diſputer, no Martyr to be found? what, not one that retained any ſpark of zeal for Chriſt, that after ages could ſpeak of, either o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th approbation or deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for willingly ſuffering ſhame, ſpoyling of goods, baniſhment, death, rather then Chriſt ſhould be pull'd down in his worſhip, and a Nationall falſe Church-government ſet up in the roome of it? I cannot but wonder that all Chriſtian Churches ſhould fall at once into ſuch a dead ſleep, to ſuffer the evill <hi>One</hi> thus to pluck up, and thus to plant; or elſe, if their eyes were open, I cannot but call it the greateſt piece of cow ardiſe that ever the Churches of Chriſt were guilty of, to ſtand idle, ſpeechleſſe ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors by; where was the valour of their faith? <hi>Heb. 11.33, 34.</hi> Or if they did diſpute and ſuffer for it, I cannot but think it the greateſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe and overſight the Churches were ever guilty of, not to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſtory to poſterity.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, this <hi>Argument</hi> impleadeth <hi>Presbyterie</hi> as well as <hi>Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall</hi> government; for where read we of ſufferers for <hi>Presbytery?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, To come more directly to the point, you grant the Churches conſtituted by the Apoſtles <hi>Congregationall;</hi> now if wee ſhew this practice of theirs was intended, as a pattern for us, and ſo taken by the moſt Primitive Churches, we hope your demand will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113141:5"/>be ſatisfied, though wee could not diſtinctly ſhew you why none appeared in the defence of it—of which anon.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, God and nature do nothing in vain, was the ſaying of the ancient Naturaliſts; the Spirit of God did ſo diſtinctly ſet down the manner of the conſtitution of the Jewiſh Church by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that poſterity may have a diſtinct pattern as wel as a rule to walk by, the Holy Ghoſt hath to ſome purpoſe ſurely, ſo punctually noted the manner of gathering and governing the Churches planted by the Apoſtles, and what can this purpoſe be, but our imitation in things lawfull and poſſible? for all in the new, as well as in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are written for our learning, and <hi>follow me,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, and that by way of forbearing, and negatively, as by way of doing, and affirmatively; that is, wee may not do what they did not, when they might, and the nature of the thing ſeemed to require it, (as the ſubjecting particular Churches to a combination of Elders, which ſhould have ordinary authority over the ſeverall Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations) which they might have done, as well as to keep up the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in one city, which they did; and as well as the Church of <hi>France</hi> at this day, though under perſecution, yet keep their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and when by reaſon of the paucity of believers, and the temptation of perſecution, they had much need of the help of government, and no hinderance why they might not, ſeeing though by reaſon of perſecution they might have been hindered for a time, and in ſome places, yet the rule of ſuch a government, if it had been the will of God, had been uſefull, and though they had been diſturbed in one place, yet it would have been exerciſed in ſome other; this was a ſufficient argument for God to uſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.31. they did — <hi>which I commanded them not:</hi> and for the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.14. of which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake nothing, <hi>Ergo,</hi> God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it not. And ſo affirmatively, what they did for ſubſtance, we muſt: Hence <hi>Gualter</hi> in the end of his Comment on the <hi>Acts,</hi> ſayes they are not to be liſtened unto that tell us the way and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Apoſtles in conſtituting Churches, is not a pattern for us to follow.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The Churches in the firſt and ſecond hundred yeers after Chriſt, did take the Apoſtles practice for their pattern, and therefore every Church did tranſact all their ordinary affaires within themſelves, as admiſſion of members, choyce and ordination
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113141:5"/>of officers, excommunication of ſcandalous perſons, depoſition of their officers, where juſt cauſe was; in difficult caſes indeed, they uſed the counſell and help of other Churches, but as being ingaged thereunto only out of the bond of mutuall love and fellowſhip; not of neceſſity or ſubjection; and where any Church was more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for gifts, numbers, Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to theſe they gave the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſpects, and did more depend upon their guidance; till this voluntary and occaſionall office of love became a cuſtome, <hi>viz.</hi> for the leſſer and obſcurer Churches, to do nothing without the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and for the greater, to exerciſe inſpection, and ſome kinde of juriſdiction towards the leſſer, by way of charge and office, till in the third Century it was by the Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> — eſtabliſhed by a Canon for a Church-law; at which time <hi>Antichriſt</hi> had made much progreſſe towards his uſurpation: For proof of all which, I ſhall ſhew you ſome of the words of the Centurie Writers touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Argument; and firſt of the conſtitution of Churches plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Apoſtles: 1. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>de gubernatione Eccleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titul. de conſociatione,</hi> &amp;c. If it be ſaid theſe conſiſted of many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and ſo were <hi>Presbyteriall,</hi> I anſwer, it cannot be proved they were ſo; ſecondly, nor diſproved, that they were one congregation; becauſe we reade ſo often, both in Scripturall and Eccleſiaſticall ſtory that they had one Elderſhip, not ſeverall over them, and that they all met upon one great occaſion together, as upon the choice or depoſition of Miniſters, excommunication of members, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if they did meet in ſeverall places, yet having one Elderſhip over them, and not ſeverall Elderſhips for the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall companies, and not being tied any of them to come to any one place more then another; it doth no more argue they were many congregations, or hinder their being one (though inconvenient to be governed by reaſon of its vaſtneſſe) then it doth in <hi>Holland,</hi> where the caſe is ſo, or then in ſome great pariſhes in and about <hi>London;</hi> where, though they meet in one place, yet cannot meet all together, by reaſon of the multitude, being above 10000. in ſome pariſhes, unleſſe at ſeverall times, if it were ſo, that they had been <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> in a city, yet it is far different from that government that makes many towns &amp; cities one Church, and drawes them to ſubjection to one common <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and that in ordinary, againſt which many Reaſons might be given, though the other were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113141:6"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, If the Churches of thoſe times had not ſo judged that the Way the Apoſtles left Churches in was to be their pattern, as it had been eaſie for them to order it; (as afterward their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity did into Epiſcopacie) ſo had it been more advantage and eaſe to them, to have united many Churches together into one body, and to ſet one Councell and Preſident over it, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of Hereſies, Schiſmes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which yet they did not, till times grew more corrupt, and which at this day is the ſtate of the Papacie.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Though this might ſuffice, yet I ſhall now ſhew you how it might come to paſſe, that this received truth might be loſt, and no notice left of any contending for it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, greater truths then this of government have been ſtolen from the Church without any great reluctancy: As far as appears; as the reading of the Scriptures by the people, tranſubſtantiation of the bread in the Sacrament, adoration of the Hoſt, the Maſſe it ſelf, taking the cup from the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which the ſubtilty of men taking advantage by the negligence and cowardiſe of the people, brought in without much oppoſition till long after.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the monuments of antiquity in this kinde, are very defective; firſt, by the notable careleſneſſe of Writers in thoſe times, of which, <hi>Ludovicus, apud Illyricum, in Refutat.</hi> Brin. <hi>pag.</hi> 15. an Author of no mean credit, complains, It is a ſingular grief to me (ſaith he) when I call to minde, how diligently the actions of <hi>Alexander, Scipio, Annibal, Pompey, Ceſar, Socrates, Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> and other Captains and Philoſophers, have been noted, that there is no perill of their periſhing, but the doings of the Apoſtles (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as are ſet down in ſacred Scripture) Martyrs and Saints of our Religion; yea, and of the Church it ſelf, whether growing up, or at full age, are covered in deep ſilence; for theſe things which are written, excepting a few only, are corrupted with feigned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thus hee a man by profeſſion a Papiſt. Secondly, becauſe of the prevalencie of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> faction, whereby all monuments, almoſt, that ſeemed to oppoſe the intended uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as the ancient government of the Churches eſpecially did) were either ſpupreſſed, or ſome way violated, as (amongſt many others) D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>James</hi> hath diſcovered at large in his book entituled, <hi>The Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. But,</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113141:6"/>
                  <p>Laſtly, to give you a more direct anſwer, there have not been wanting defendents of the liberties of the Churches in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; for ſeeing it is evident by the firſt, ſecond and third particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in this anſwer, that both in the Apoſtles times, and next ages after, the Churches were governed each by themſelves (as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of authority out of their own body) if there were any that reſiſted thoſe that invaded that liberty, thoſe are the examples of ſuffering (or at leaſt conteſting) for this government, but the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were the firſt that uſurped the power of many Churches, <hi>in ordinary,</hi> and theſe were often reſiſted by word, writing and fact, as appeares, not only by <hi>Aerius</hi> (who was counted an Heretique for his labour) but alſo by <hi>Jerom,</hi> who ſaith, that Biſhops were brought in to prevent Hereſies and Schiſmes, but that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were anciently governed by the joynt counſell of the Elders. Now this was either by the Elders of the ſame Church, or if with others, it was a conjunction by way of Chriſtian fellowſhip and ſociety, not by juriſdiction, authority, and neceſſity, (as wee ſaw before) I adde, that the ſufferings of ſo many in oppoſition to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall government even in the ancient times, is an argument in a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative ſenſe, that there hath been ſufferings for Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe they would not ſubmit to a falſe government: To conclude this argument, I ſhall endeavour at better leiſure to give you ſome particular inſtances out of the ſtory, which maymore fully ſatisfie this Querie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Inſigniores Eccleſiae,</hi> &amp;c. They which were more eminent Churches (ſay they) were in ſome honour becauſe of the Apoſtles that taught in them, and becauſe of their Miniſters that were more excellent for learning and conſtancy, and likewiſe of the benefits that thoſe Churches did afford to other neighbour Churches, but they had no other power over other Churches, then by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall offices in things belonging to the edification of the whole Church, to afford them their help: and then inſtances in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <q>The Churches in the next age after the Apoſtles, <hi>Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>titul. de conſociatione Eccleſiarum. Caeterum ſi quis probatos au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores,</hi> &amp;c. If (ſay they) any man look into the approved Authors of this age, hee ſhall find, that the form of government was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt like a popular government; for every Church had equall</q>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113141:7"/>
                     <q>power, to preach the Word of God purely, to adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, to abſolve and excommunicate heretiques, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men,—to elect, call and ordain Miniſters, and upon ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient grounds to depoſe them, to call aſſemblies and Synods,—in doubtfull things, and that were controverſall, to require the opinions of others, to judge and determine them. Further, the neighbour Churches for charity and edification ſake, not for any ſuperiour juriſdiction, but for the command of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning mutuall love, in their neceſſity craved the help of their neighbour Churches, and alſo afforded theirs to them.—in more weighty queſtions, all the Churches or Elders of that Province, or elſe the moſt of the Teachers came together, and determined by common advice what was to be done; for the faithfull in <hi>Aſia</hi> (ſaith <hi>Euſebius,</hi> quoted by them in that place) came often from many places together, and examined the new doctrines, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced them wicked, and rejecting the hereſie, they caſt and excommunicated it out of the Church.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The Churches that were farther off, in other Provinces, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with other Churches by letters, which they did generally, or by common conſent ſubſcribe; this new propheſie (ſaith <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> in <hi>Euſeb.</hi> cited by the <hi>Cent.</hi>) is refuted and rejected by all the brotherhood which is in all the world.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Tit. de Synodis privat.</hi> each Church (that things might be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ordered) had their Synod or aſſemblies or Church-meetings, in which the Rector (or Paſtor) the Elders, the Deacons, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the people did deliberate and determine of things belonging to the government of the Church.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <q>The Churches in the third hundred yeer, <hi>Cen.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Tit. de Synodis privatis in principio.</hi> Now that the juriſdiction of the great Churches over the leſſe was eſtabliſhed, and the authority of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitanes determined by the <hi>Nicene Councel;</hi> yet, if any buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe happened, which could not be perfected without the reſt, both Miniſters &amp; people, then they came together and diſpatched them with common advice, without the calling of the Churches of the ſame Province: So <hi>Cyprian</hi> (cited by them) <hi>Epiſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. From the beginning of my being Biſhop, (or Paſtor) I determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to do nothing without your counſell (hee ſpeaks to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Deacons) nor without the conſent of the people, by my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113141:7"/>own private opinion. — In theſe aſſemblies in other Churches, there were few orders made by the Biſhops or Paſtors, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards approved by the Church, unleſſe it was in <hi>Rome,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the efficacy of <hi>the myſterie of Iniquity.</hi> (they are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors words) ſome Biſhops made decrees as <hi>Damaſus, Galixtus,</hi> &amp;c.</q> By all which it appeares, that the Churches moſt Primitive were ignorant of any neceſſity or law lying on them, to be governed by one Church, or more, or of aſſociating with any, but as they ſaw cauſe, and by the law of charity, neither underſtood there was any Provinciall, much leſſe Nationall or univerſall and miniſteriall and governing Church, which muſt by way of authority diſpoſe of all the affaires of the particular Churches.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But they excommunicated in their Aſſemblies of many Churches?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. So did they in each particular Church, as of their own right, and conſulted not with others, unleſſe the cauſe was difficult.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The excommunication was rather of the opinion by dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and condemning of it, then of perſons.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If there were ſuch excommunication of perſons, yet it was done by the willing conſent of the Churches, or elſe for themſelves; thoſe Churches that met not for others, unleſſe by conſequent, that he who is excommunicated out of one Church, if it be duly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, is excommunicated out of all.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT II.</head>
               <p>WHy hath not the civill Magiſtrate a power to ſet up and eſtabliſh by a law ſuch a worſhip as an Aſſembly of godly Divines ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them to be according to the Word of God, as well as they had a power to pull down falſe worſhip, Popery, Epiſcopacie, Arminianiſme, and ſuch groſſe errors and innovations as had juſtled out the true ſervants and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God? and this they did with the approbations and acclamations of all thoſe that profeſſed the power of godlineſſe, of what Way or Sect ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were; I never heard of any ſuch, that accuſed them for ſtretching beyond their line therein. If the ſubject matter of Politicall adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be meerly humane matters, why did not Congregationall Divines inform them as much, but were ſilent while they had their hands thruſt deep into Church-affaires, and things ſpirituall? Why did not their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113141:8"/>jealouſie over the Parliament break out when they ſaw them begin to daſh the foot againſt that ſtone, but gave thanks to God for them &amp; their doing; but now when they have come to ſet up, and it proves aworſhip againſt their judgement and conſcience, they are reproved, and have no power at all in things Eccleſiaſticall, but every man muſt enjoy his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, worſhip and way? If they once had a power to pull down, why have they not now power to pull down in the like caſe, with the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned approbation? and if in things Eccleſiaſticall they have a power to pull down, why not to ſet up too? That the civill Magiſtrate ſhall have a power in things ſpirituall, and yet no power, is a myſterie unto mee.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THe government the Magiſtrate hath pulled down, was ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as a Law of the kingdome, and by that power was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to the perſecution of the Saints, and diſturbance of the State, which was the defection of the Magiſtracie of theſe times. Now when the Magiſtrates ſhall not only withdraw their power, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo prohibit the further exerciſe thereof in the perſecution of the Saints and diſturbance of the State; we ſuppoſe it is no more then according to their juſt power, and therefore do rejoyce therein.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Magiſtrates juſt doing any thing according to the joynt conſent, deſire, approbation, and congratulatory acclamations of all the Saints, is no good argument to prove a lawfull power in the Magiſtrate to do things contrary to the joynt conſent, deſires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of all the Saints. <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate, Felix</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> had a juſt power to releaſe Chriſt and <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c. but that doth not argue that their power was juſt in delivering them up unto whipping, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it was indeed <hi>potentia,</hi> but not <hi>poteſtas,</hi> might, but not right, and it is the latter, I ſuppoſe, that you mean.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We did never deny the Magiſtrate a lawfull power to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with that kinde of Church-government or doctrine, (opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or practice) which ſhall moſt dangerouſly intermeddle with the State it ſelf; and thereby prove evidently hurtfull, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently deſtructive thereunto, and ſo did the government whereof you ſpeak, which was the ground of that act of aboliſhing the ſame. When Congregationall or Presbyteriall government, or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof be found in their principles and generall practices,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113141:8"/>underminers of the peace and welfare of the kingdome, raiſing up wars and trouble to maintain the ſame, it is high time for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, who is mainly to minde <hi>ſalutem populi,</hi> to pull them down, and no longer to tolerate the ſame, and ſuch is the inſtance which you ſpeak of.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Thoſe Chriſtian or unchriſtian Magiſtrates may have a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full power and authority to deſtroy <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which may have no lawfull authority to appoint lawes and rules for the government of the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, and to enforce the ſame contrary to their judgements and conſciences; <hi>Cyrus</hi> may have a juſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from God for the ruining of <hi>Babylon;</hi> but not for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of <hi>Sion</hi> to worſhip God according to his thoughts of the will of God therein, all Magiſtrates may, and ought to aſſiſt and preſerve the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt from thoſe that wonld ruine and deſtroy them, but that any magiſtrate hath power to compell the Saints of God what to believe in matters of faith, and what to practice in matters of immediate worſhip (eſpecially in things that are of <hi>an intricate and deep cognizance,</hi> and controverſall among the godly learned) (<hi>which is the main buſineſſe in hand,</hi> between the Presbyterian and Independent party) is beyond any ground that I can yet perceive from the Scriptures; but we ſhall meet with this again in another of your Arguments.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. III.</head>
               <p>VVHy do not our Congregationall Divines write to the Brethren of <hi>New-England,</hi> and convince them of their errour, who give (as ſome ſay) the civill Magiſtrate a power to queſtion doctrines, cenſure errours? ſure we are, ſome have been impriſoned, ſome baniſhed, that [pleaded] Religion and meere conſcience, and were no otherwiſe diſturbers of the civill peace, then the Congregationall Way is like to be here: So that if our Magiſtrates and Presbyters muſt be ruled by <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliels</hi> advice, and ſuffer all opinions till God diſclaim and fight againſt them from heaven, why is not his advice ſent over to them, leſt they ſhould fight againſt any Way that calls God father? If <hi>Old-England</hi> be ſaid to perſecute, for ſuppreſſing Sects and Opinions, becauſe threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth, and civill peace, why may not the ſame name be put upon <hi>New-England,</hi> who are found in the ſame work and Way? and if
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113141:9"/>both he guilty, 'twere wiſdome and piety for our Congregationall Divines to eaſt the firſt ſtone at themſelves, I mean, their Congregationall Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to convince and perſwade them to ſuffer all Opinions amongst them, this would be an argument that they walk in all ſimplicity and ſincerity of ſpirit preferring Gods will and the naked truth, above any ends of their own, (whereof ſome ſuſpect them, how juſtly, God the ſearcher of hearts knowes) and next their arguments and perſwaſions would be more eaſily received at home.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>THis is an Argument, or rather an Inſinuation to the accuſing of our Brethren, then to the finding out the truth; but to this I anſwer:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, in relation to our Brethrens practice in <hi>New-England,</hi> I anſwer you in this caſe, as the father of the blind man anſwered the <hi>Phariſees</hi> about the manner of procuring his ſons ſight, <hi>Job.</hi> 9.21. <hi>He is of age, ask him;</hi> ſo ſay I, they are able to anſwer for themſelves, if not, they ſtand or fall to their own Maſter; But,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I ſuppoſe it is eaſier to affirm then to prove that any were impriſoned or baniſhed meerely for their conſciences, wee have a common Proverb, <hi>That untruths loſe nothing by diſtance of place,</hi> and by often reporting, ſome affirm it hath been ſo, as you ſay; others deny the ſame; for my part, becauſe I have more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe the one then the other (becauſe the Magiſtrates them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deny any perſecution meerly for a mans private conſcience, in the caſe of M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
                     <hi>Hutchiſon,</hi> See the book [the riſe and end of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomianiſme</hi> in <hi>New-England, p.</hi> 46. of the firſt <hi>Edition;</hi>) I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looke unto theſe things that do concern us at home, then to go ſo far to accuſe our brethren abroad.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I humbly ſuppoſe it is out of your certain knowledge that the Congregationall Divines have not at all written unto their Brethren of <hi>New-England</hi> about this buſineſs, and have not received ſatisfaction herein, I ſuppoſe likewiſe, I have as much reaſon, if not more, to affirm that they have, as you that they have not; But,</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, ſuppoſe they have not written, this will prove but the remiſneſſe of their duty at the moſt, and will not facilitate and eaſe the buſineſſe in the leaſt; doubtleſſe the Presbyterian party in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113141:9"/>other parts of the world not all things according to the minde of God, even in the judgements of the Brethren-Presbyterians of this Nation; and if ſo, may not the ſame thing be retorted upon them which you do here upon theſe?</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, As for thoſe jealouſies which you ſay are in ſome about the Congregationall Brethrens <hi>ſimplicity and ſincerity of ſpirit in preferring Gods Will and the naked Truth above any ends of their own,</hi> as Gods royall Prerogative in ſearching all hearts, ſhould ſtifle ſuch miſpriſions, and quit all ſuch unworthy ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſings, till better proofe appeare; ſo any mans reaſons (not maſtered with prejudice and diſcontent) ſhould fully diſcharge all ſuch vain, unworthy, and uncharitable imaginations concerning their Brethren; for except mens ends and aims ſhould be ſorrow, trouble, reproach and contempt, perplexity and miſery, penury and want, what other ends can they have? Are not ſome of theſe for the preſent, and all of them for the future, the threatened iſſues, products and conſequences of their wayes and practices? Surely men ſhould make a better uſe of their own perſonall weakneſſes, <hi>viz.</hi> their own ſinfull ends and aims, and by-reſpects in their own hearts, then to make them the meaſure and rule to judge of their Brethrens hearts by; every man ſhould think better of his brother then of himſelf; ſurely the men of their jealouſies are not uſually ſteer'd up and down from one place to another, by the golden lure of an hundred, or two or three hundred a yeer, as many of their cenſorious Judges are, but it is worthy our obſervation; the Saints of our moſt high God, many times are chiefly charged for thoſe things whereof they are leaſt guilty, and where they are moſt innocent, and therefore moſt able to beare the ſame: Thus <hi>Joſeph</hi> for incontinency; <hi>Eliſha</hi> for the troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (though indeed the horſemen and chariots of <hi>Iſrael;</hi>) thus <hi>David</hi> for ſeeking <hi>Sauls</hi> life, whoſe heart ſmote him for but cutting off one of the skirts of his garment; thus Jeſus Chriſt for a deceiver (who was the truth it ſelf,) and for a familiar with the Prince of the Devils, who was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the great enemy to him and his works: and as it was from the beginning, ſo it is now, the humble, the meek, the ſimple-hearted, the peaceable, the moſt forward for reformation; yea, when their zeale therein caſt them into impriſonments, ſorrows, troubles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe men (I ſay) are under jealouſies, nay, evident and expreſſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113141:10"/>cenſures of being proud, perverſe, deceitfull, diſturbers of the peace of the State, hinderers of Reformation, with many ſuch like and unworthy reproaches, but the faithfull Witneſſe and Judge of all hearts will one day bring forth their innocency as the light, and in the mean while ſupport their ſpirits under all thoſe hard ſpeeches, thoughts and calumnies of this world.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. IV.</head>
               <p>TItus 1.10, 11. There are many unruly talkers, and deceivers, who ſubvert whole houſes, teaching things which they ought not, whoſe mouths muſt be ſtopped: But Church-cenſure or ſentence of non-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, will not ſtop their mouths; for (as tis in the <hi>Apologeticall Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>) they being of another way and judgement, it binds not their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſo dare piſh at the ſentence of Non-communion of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, let the Presbyterians pronounce a ſentence againſt Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Churches; or let Congregationall Churches pronounce any ſentence againſt Presbyterians, Antinomians, Anabaptiſts, who will teach things, as they thinke, which they ought not, and ſee when this ſentence ſtops their mouths: But <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, Their mouths muſt be ſtopped, Church-cenſure does it not; therefore, if they muſt be ſtopped, the civill Magiſtrate muſt ſtrike in to ſtop them, elſe they will ever be open to ſubvert whole houſes. In the Apoſtles times, what Church-cenſure could not reach to, was left to the power and providence of God to ſubdue and maſter, and ſupply the office of a Magiſtrate; but now when God has bleſt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Commonwealth with a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, if Church-cenſure will not ſtop deceivers mouths, but ſtill they will ſubvert mens precious ſoules, the Magiſtrate muſt exerciſe his power, for they muſt be ſtopped.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, whereas the Apoſtle tels <hi>Titus,</hi> that ſuch unruly talkers and deceivers mouths muſt be ſtopt, it is cleer, that it is <hi>Titus</hi> that muſt ſtop them, for otherwayes the Apoſtle writes unto him to no purpoſe, and hee directs him likewiſe which way hee ſhould ſtop their mouths, <hi>viz.</hi> verſ. 13. <hi>Rebuke them ſharply, that they may be ſound in the faith,</hi> and in the firſt <hi>verſe</hi> of the next <hi>Chapter, but ſpeak thou the things which become ſound doctrine;</hi> and <hi>verſe</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113141:10"/>ſaith of <hi>ſound ſpeech</hi> that it <hi>cannot be condemned.</hi> Surely, in that ſenſe that <hi>Titus</hi> may be ſaid to hinder them from condemning ſound ſpeech, he may be ſaid to ſtop their mouths; you know in Scripture language, a mans mouth is ſaid to be ſtopt, when he is not able to gain-ſay the power of reaſon and arguments that are oppoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: So <hi>Luke</hi> 21.15. Chriſt promiſeth his Diſciples <hi>to give them a mouth and wiſdome, which all their adverſaries ſhould not be able to gain-ſay nor reſiſt;</hi> that is, which ſhall ſtop their mouths, <hi>viz.</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatively: So <hi>Acts</hi> 6.10. <hi>Stephen</hi> ſo ſpake, that the <hi>Cyrenians</hi> and <hi>Alexandrians were not able to reſiſt the wiſdome and ſpirit by which hee ſpake;</hi> So <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.34. Chriſt is ſaid to put the <hi>Sadduces</hi> to ſilence, that is, to ſtop their mouths, and <hi>verſ.</hi> 46. the <hi>Phariſees</hi> likewiſe were not able to anſwer him a word, and (to name no more places) 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. the will of God is, that <hi>by well doing wee ſhould put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi> You know there is nothing doth more open their mouths, then the well doing of the Saints; but they open not their mouths like men: ſo here their mouths muſt be ſtopt, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Titus</hi> his ſound words: this I humbly conceive is as cleer as the day; and to make it ſo, you have the ſame phraſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. that <hi>every mouth muſt be ſtopped.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, whereas you ſay, that that which Church-cenſure could not do was left to the power and providence of God to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due and maſter, and ſupply the office of a Magiſtrate, I anſwer, that though it was left to the power and providence of God to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due and maſter, yet that this was to ſupply the office of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is but <hi>petitio principii,</hi> and therefore your inference, that now when God hath bleſt a Chriſtian Commonwealth with Chriſtian Magiſtrates, hee muſt ſtop their mouths, is likewiſe taken before given.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, if by ſtopping their mouths, you mean directly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the literall ſenſe of the words, the Magiſtrate neither can ſtop their mouths, except he will cut out their tongues, or ſow up their lips, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for they will be ſpeaking where ever they are.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GAlat. 5.11, 12.</hi> There were ſome that preached circumciſion and Chriſt together; this hotch potch-doctrine much prevailed, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113141:11"/>troubled the Churches, and <hi>Paul</hi> ſighs and gromes out this wiſh; <hi>I would they were cut off that trouble you.</hi> The queſtion is, what kinde of cutting off hee means, is it by Church-cenſure? then hee might ſoone have eaſed himſelf and the Churches of them, himſelf might have excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated them, as he did <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> 1 Time 1.20. or commanded the Churches, when they had been gathered together, and his ſpirit, with the power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to have delivered ſuch up unto Satan, <hi>1 Cor. 5.4, 5.</hi> but this hee did not, on if hee did, it would not ſerve his and the Churches turn, he and they ſtill groan under the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of falſe Teachers; therefore it muſt be meant of a cutting off by ſome ſpeciall extraordinary providence of God, their deſtruction by the divine hand of juſtice. Whence I think this note may genuinely be collected, The Church of God may be peſtered with falſe Teachers, which no Church-cenſure will ſo cut off, as that they can be freed of them, and therefore the civill Magiſtrate by his power (God having left off extraordinary mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foſtations of juſtice againſt his and his Churches enemies) muſt cut them off, and not ſuffer the Churches to be troubled and ſowred with the leaven of their doctrine.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>I Anſwer, by cutting off there, you ſuppoſe, not to be meant Church-cenſure, and you give reaſons for it, but you think it was ſome ſpeciall, extraordinary providence of God in bringing to paſſe their deſtruction, and I think ſo too, though it may be meant alſo of Church-cenſure, which the Apoſtle could have wiſhed, might have been done, but the ſtate of thoſe Churches could not beare it; but for that you infer that becauſe now Church-cenſure cannot reach them, therefore the civill Magiſtrate by his power (God having left off extraordinary manifeſtations of juſtice againſt his and his Churches enemies) muſt cut them off, and not ſuffer the Churches to be leavened and ſowred with ſuch leaven of their doctrine. But, Sir, I humbly deny your inference; for if Magiſtrates have a lawfull power to ſupply the extraordinary inſtances of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which God hathgiven in the puniſhment of ſin, if, I ſay, Magiſtrates have a power thus to do in your ſenſe, why then the Magiſtrate ſhould kill and deſtroy liers, becauſe God by an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſtroke of juſtice did kill <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira, Acts</hi> 5.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113141:11"/>for telling a lie, the Magiſtrate ſhould deſtroy men for ſleeping at hearing the Word, becauſe <hi>Eutychus</hi> by an extraordinary hand of divine juſtice fell down dead from an upper loft where hee was ſleeping when hee ſhould be hearing the Word of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. Nay, which is more abſurd, <hi>Magiſtrates ſhould then omit the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of juſtice upon more notorious ſinners,</hi> and deſtroy the leſſe guilty ſinners; yea, and ſhould be at an uncertainty herein, becauſe Gods juſtice hath reached ſome, and ſpared others guilty of the ſame ſins; yea, much greater, which I preſume you will judge abſurd; for the Magiſtrate is to execute juſtice according to a known juſt law, and not according to the example of God, who may deſtroy for an idle thought, if hee pleaſeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REv. 2.</hi> God has ſomething to ſay againſt the Church in <hi>Pergamos,</hi> becauſe ſhee had thoſe that taught the doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and theſe alſo that held the doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> (i.) they had them ſtill, their mouths open, teaching theſe doctrines, not ſuppreſſed, not taken out of the way. And ſomething he had againſt the Churches in <hi>Thya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tira,</hi> becauſe they ſuffered that woman <hi>Jezabel</hi> to teach and ſeduce his. ſervants, either thoſe that actually were his ſervants, or thoſe that poſſibly (for ought they knew) might have been his ſervants; her they ſhould not have ſuffered to have taught and ſpread her infectious errors, though. doubtleſſe, ſhee being a Propheteſſe was able to have ſaid much for her, Way, and would have pleaded conſcience too, yet 'tis a charge drawn up againſt them, that ſhe is ſuffered, and to mee it ſeemes by the Antitheſis, to run thus; <hi>verſ. 22.</hi> Behold (as if hee had ſaid) though you have fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the execution of juſtice upon her, yet behold, I will caſt her into great tribulation, and will kill her and her children with death; I will not ſuffer her, I will not faile in doing juſtice upon her and her children, as you ſinfully have done. Church-cenſure only would not have bindered her from teaching, but ſhee was not to have been ſuffered to teach, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a further power ought to have come in for the ſuppreſſion of her and her followers.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113141:12"/>
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, I humbly conceive, that Church-cenſures, if duly and timely performed, would have prevented this reproofe, both to the one Church and the other, and the neglect hereof, or (which is worſe) the not ſuppreſſing theſe falſe doctrines by a powerfull preaching againſt the ſame, was the ground of theſe ſharp and bitter reproofs, and my Reaſon is this; it is evident they had not the help of the Magiſtrate therein: for in reſpect of the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſtate, it is ſaid of the Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> that ſhee dwelt where Satan had his ſeat, or throne, and where <hi>Antipas</hi> (Gods faithfull ſervant) ſuffered martyrdome; ſo that they had no help in that reſpect from the Magiſtrate, and if ſo, I ſuppoſe you will not ſay the Church could impriſon, baniſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that I preſume their neglect muſt be of ſomething which was in the power of the Church; And,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, whereas you ſay, Church-cenſures would not have hindered theſe proceedings in the Church, I humbly conceive the contrary, becauſe, if the Church officers and members had exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theſe doctrines as they ought, and upon the finding of them er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, had proceeded to cenſure them, in caſe they would not forbeare the promulgation thereof, from that time the Church was not to permit them to preach any more amongſt them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould they give them any more hearing.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, If a means ſanctified by God to an end, do not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes effect it, wee may not therefore deviſe another, Magiſtracy doth not ſuppreſſe all vice.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT VII.</head>
               <p>MOſt evident it is, that the civill Magiſtrate in the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was ſupreme in things Eccleſiaſtic ill, <hi>1 Chro. 15. David</hi> aſſembles all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> gives the Prieſts and Levites their charge, orders the things of the Ark of God, <hi>verſ. 1.</hi> to <hi>18. 2 Chron. 15.</hi> Its ſaid, King <hi>Aſa</hi> took courage, and put away the abominable Idols, and renewed the Altar of the Lord, and made a Covenant, and whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhould be put to death,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113141:12"/>whether great or ſmall, man or woman. Now let it be ſhowne, where God took this power from the civill Magiſtrate under the new Teſtament; why the Magiſtrate has not as much power, or the ſame power in matters Eccleſiaſticall, as then hee had? 'Tis true, the Apoſtles were very ſilent, and cloſe in giving the civill Magiſtrate his juſt power in things ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but I conceive this cloſeneſs of theirs was their prudence, and that in theſe two reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There was no Magiſtrate then, but <hi>Heathoniſh</hi> or <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> and ſo underſtood not Gods will in his worſhip; and ſo had any thing been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, it had been but a oarnall commandement, humane, which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt have refuſed, and therefore 'twas not their wiſdome to ſpeak or write much to this point, leſt it had proved a ſnare.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Had they ſpoken much of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, that ſhould have power in things civill and Eccleſiaſticall, and be able to defend Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity againſt all it's enemies, this would have bred jealouſies in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> State, and Chriſtian Churches would have been looked upon as a conſpiring trayterous generation, and perſecutions would have ſoon been raiſed up againſt them; It was the Apoſtles wiſdome to keep <hi>Ceſars</hi> head free from jealouſies, that ſo the Churches might enjoy Chriſt, and their conſciences the better, therefore they ſpake ſo little of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate in things civill and Eccleſiaſticall, well knowing, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages would not be at a loſſe, or ſtand in this point, but might look upon the examples of the godly Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their imitation, (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver being repealed) and in <hi>David, Joſiah, Aſa,</hi> might ſee what was their right and juſt power in matters both of Church and State.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, it is not to be denyed, but that the civill Magiſtrates in the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were ſupreme in things Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but upon ſuch grounds and reaſons as were peculiar unto them; and therefore not preſidentiall for Chriſtian Magiſtrates under the Goſpel, except upon the ſame or the like grounds; For,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the godly Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were types of Chriſt: thus <hi>David,</hi> whom you inſtance, it is ſaid of him, <hi>Pſal. 75.3. The earth and all the inhabitants thereof are diſſolved; I beare up the pillars therof,</hi> which is true only of Jeſus Chriſt the antitype, who <hi>laid the foundations of the earth,</hi> Heb. 1.10. <hi>and upholdeth all things by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113141:13"/>the word of his power,</hi> verſ. 3. Now, when the antitype is come into the world, Jeſus Chriſt in the room of his father <hi>David;</hi> the law henceforth is to proceed from his lips, and the government is to be upon his ſhoulders, and of his Kingdome there ſhall be no end, <hi>Iſa. 9.6, 7.</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> was a chief magiſtrate unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unto whom they were to hearken, untill Chriſt, whom he did typifie, was come, and of him he ſaith himſelf, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 18.15. <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you like unto me, him ſhall you heare in all things whatſoever hee ſhall ſay unto you: And it ſhall come to paſſe, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall not heare that Prophet, that ſoul ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people,</hi> Acts 3.22, 23. The Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> whom you mention, are types of Chriſts kingly office, Chriſt therefore being come, the types are gone; for though kings of Commonwealths may be of a morall conſideration, and ſo perpetuall; yet kings as the head of the Church in things Eceleſiaſticall were types, and therefore aboliſhed; and by the ſame argument, as you will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the power of Chriſtian kings over the Churches of God in things meerly Eccleſiaſticall, from the examples of the kings of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> who were types of Chriſt, by the ſame arguments may the <hi>Pope</hi> maintain a chief Prieſthood under the Goſpel after the example of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the reſt of that order ſucceſſively.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the godly kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were directed by the infallible mouth of God, and guidance of his Spirit, even in theſe Eccleſiaſticall buſineſſes; and thus <hi>David,</hi> whom you in ſtance to give the Prieſts and Levites their charge, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. if you look into 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.12. he had his direction from the Spirit of God, and <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. <hi>David</hi> profeſſeth, that the Lord made him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all the work of this pattern. When you can prove ſuch an infallible guidance and direction by the Spirit of God in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Church-government to be the portion of Chriſtian kings under the Goſpel, there may be ſome colour in this argument.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were Elders of one miniſteriall congregation; for the whole Church and State were ſo, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and what they did, unleſſe upon expreſſe, either Text or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, was done with the conſent of the congregation, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, I do not remember that ever they did baniſh, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes puniſh all ſtrangers from among them, that were not of their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113141:13"/>own Religion, or had ſuch a commiſſion ſo to do, and that theſe ſevere lawes about Church-government did belong unto any but their own nation and people, or thoſe that joyned themſelves to them; all that acknowledged the ſeven precepts of <hi>Noah</hi> they tolerated, <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Moſt evident it is, that they did ſuffer ſeverall Sects, and differing Opinions among them, and that of a more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence then is the difference that is the difference that is between the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian and Independent, as the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> the <hi>Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Alexandrians,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore you may after their example plead for the like toleration, or rather for the toleration of thoſe that are of leſſe danger.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, But if any thing muſt be added, for concluſion, we ſay as the Chriſtians of old, leaving the diſpute of the Magiſtrates power, in generall, we ſay this Way being of God, at leaſt in great proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, the Magiſtrate hath no power to ſuppreſſe it, (which I deſire you to take as a full anſwer) thoſe kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> commanded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the expreſſe will of God, and that without infringing the liberties of the Congregation, whoſe conſent they had, which two things, if our Magiſtrates ſhall do, all that wee ſhall ſay, will be, <hi>Go on and proſper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seventhly, Whereas you ſay, <hi>Let it be ſhewne where God took this power from the civill Magiſtrate under the new Teſtament,</hi> &amp;c. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, where wee finde types and ceremonies taken away, there wee finde this power in matters of Church-government taken away, which (though it be not expreſt in ſo many plain words (as many other cermonies (granted on all hands to be taken away) are not) yet this, with others, is to be underſtood (as I humbly conceive) in that generall expreſſion of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24, 25. <hi>The law was a Schoolmaſter to bring us to Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but after that faith is come, we are no longer under a Schoolmaſter;</hi> theſe things being <hi>ſhadows of good things to come, but the body is Chriſt,</hi> Col. 2.17. And untill it can be proved that the civill government of the <hi>Jewes</hi> had nothing typicall as well as the Church, and that the kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were not typicall, in this particular, I humbly conceive it a ſufficient anſwer to that part of your Argument.</p>
                  <p>Eighthly, As for the Reaſons which you give of the Apoſtles cloſeneſſe (for ſo your word is) in declaring the power of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113141:14"/>Magiſtrates at that time, they are but conjecturall not Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and therefore may as well be denied by me, as affirmed by you, and that upon as probable grounds.</p>
                  <p>Your firſt Reaſon is, <hi>There was no Magiſtrate then, but</hi> Heathoniſh <hi>or</hi> Jewiſh, <hi>and ſo underſtood not Gods will in his worſhip, and ſo had any thing been commanded, it had been but a carnall commandement, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, which Chriſtians muſt have refuſed, and therefore it was not their wiſdome to ſpeak or write much to that point, leſt it had proved a ſnare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, that mens not underſtanding Gods will in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (whether <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Heathoniſh,</hi> Magiſtrate or not Magiſtrate) could be no juſt ground why the Apoſtles ſhould not teach them; (their work being to teach ſuch things which were not before un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) and if any thing had been commanded by them (though <hi>Heathoniſh</hi> or <hi>Jewiſh</hi>) according to the will of God, their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the ſame had not made the commandement carnall, for I ſuppoſe it is not the perſon commanding, but the nature of the thing commanded, that renders it carnall: For if a <hi>Heathen</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that which is the will of God, and a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrate that that is net the will of God, it is the <hi>Heathens</hi> command that muſt be obeyed, and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates command that muſt be diſobeyed, becauſe it muſt be the will of God, and not the authority of man that muſt be the grouud of warranted obedience, and they might have taught it without perill, by ſhewing, that though he had power in Church-affaires, yet not againſt their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as being of God, which was the only argument they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it by.</p>
                  <p>Your ſecond Reaſon is—<hi>Had the Apoſtles ſpoken much of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates power in things civill and Eccleſiaſticall, and be able to defend Chriſtianity againſt all its enemies,</hi> (what you mean by this laſt clauſe I know not) <hi>this would have bred jealouſies in the</hi> Romane <hi>State, and Chriſtian Churches would have been looked upon as a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring trayterous generation, and perſecutions would ſoon have been raiſed up againſt them; it was the Apoſtles wiſdome to keep</hi> Ceſars <hi>head from jealouſies, that ſo the Churches might enjoy Chriſt and their conſciences. the better,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I humbly anſwer, though it be true, the Saints ſhould be as wiſe, as Serpents, yet as innocent as Doves; and herein the Apoſtles ſnewed their innocency, in that they <hi>kept back nothing of the will of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113141:14"/>God that was profitable,</hi> Acts 20.20. I ſuppoſe this could not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable; and although every truth muſt be preached ſeaſonably, yet at one time or another, (your aſſerting the Apoſtles ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Saints ſufficient underſtanding the will of God about Chriſtian Magiſtrates, from Gods will revealed therein, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> being only your own conjecture, as I ſaid before, and not Scripture; doth not at all eaſe this buſineſſe) for that muſt firſt be proved before we can grant it you: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, it is evident the Apoſtles did not balk or forbeare to preach ſuch truths as were every whit as exaſperating the <hi>Roman</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate as this particular you ſpeak of: as that <hi>Jeſus was both Lord and Chriſt,</hi> Acts 2.36. and that he ſhould <hi>put down all rule and all authority, and power,</hi> yea, and that he ſhould <hi>reign untill hee hath put down all his enemies under his feet,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.24. yea, and the more they were forbidden to preach, the more they went about preaching, not regarding the command of the Magiſtrate, when it was beyond the line of his juſt authority, and many other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of this nature may be given; and theſe things (I conceive) may be ſufficient anſwers unto your 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Argument.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. VIII.</head>
               <p>I Deſire to know if <hi>Gamaliel</hi> had given the Councell this advice of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraining and letting alone, concerning <hi>Theudas</hi> or <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> I ſay, whether the Councell, being able to have demonſtrated them and their wayes erroneous, they ought to have conſented to him or no; for this is the true ſtate of the Queſtion, and not whether the Miniſters and truths of Chriſt may be ſuppreſſed, wee all know this would be fighting againſt God, to run a hazard no leſſe then death, but whether a Councell finding a generation of Teachers erring from the truth, and wilfull in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, muſt then let them alone, and expect that God ſhould fight againſt them from heaven before they would ſentence or ſmite. I am ſure <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel</hi> ſeems to approve of rejoycing in the deſtruction of thoſe two foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, with their followers, when onee they were deſtroyed; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, they were deſtroyed in an ordinary courſe of providence, by the <hi>Jews,</hi> God making no extraordinary or remarkable revelations from heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them or their errours, and therefore I conclude, it had been better to have ſentenced and quite cruſhed them in the ſhell, which had preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113141:15"/>all the miſchiefes that were done, the troubles of the State, the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſoules not a few. Mee thinks, through the ſpectacles that I looke upon the place, <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſeems cleerly to imply, that if the Councell could have diſcovered by any means, them and their doctrine not to have been of God, (as before they had done <hi>Thendas</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi>) finding them ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory as they did, they might have paſſed their own ſentence upon them, and neither God nor <hi>Gamaliel</hi> would have reproved them for it, but good ſervice they had done. So that had I been to have ſpoken to that Text, theſe three points I ſhould have inſiſted upon:</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a moſt dangerous thing to ſentence and perſecute the ſervants and truths of God; 'tis no leſſe then fighting againſt God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God ſometimes over-powers wicked men (as he did <hi>Gamaliel</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, and the reſt of the Councell to ſubmit to his advice) to make way for the ſervants and truths of God, that they may ſtand and proſper.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to oppoſe the truth of God is to fight againſt God, ſo to ſentence and oppoſe doctrines which by the cleer light of Scripture, are from men, or of a worſe deſcent, is to fight for God, and do him ſervice: this is implied. I would gladly know, how did God diſclaime or renounce from heaven, <hi>Theudas</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> with their errors, that after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels forbearing, might be a warrant for their deſtruction; what contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety unto God was diſcovered in their Wayes when they fell upon them, that was not apparent when firſt they ſhewed their heads? their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons catching and kindling in the hearts of many, might have ſtumbled the Councell into a longer forbearance of them, as being eaſily of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, that God owned them, and they went on in the power of God, and therefore now more dangerous to reſiſt them then before, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently muſt never have parted the value of the leaſt haire of their heads againſt them, till they had ſeen fire and darts come down from heaven amongst them. But doubtleſſe, their deſtruction was no otherwiſe but thus; the Councell finding their Wayes thwarting <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were ſorry for their thus long forbearance of them, ſent out forces, ſlew and ſcatter'd them, notwithſtanding their conſciences, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their errours claimed, doubtleſſe, a glorious and high deſcent. How has God diſclaimed the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> any otherwiſe then hee has done <hi>Antinomianiſme, Anabaptiſme?</hi> hee has cleerly written their condemnations with his finger in his Word, that all of them ſtand in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and oppoſition unto him and his providence [ſeemingly] never owned any Religion more under the Goſpel, then it has done Popery, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113141:15"/>therefore why muſt not their conſciences and Wayes be refrained from, as well as the others? I cannot yet ſee, how upon <hi>Gamaliels</hi> words can be grounded the forbearance, letting alone, any Way, that is once diſcovered to be not according to the rule, the Analogie of the faith of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>THat queſtion concerning the Councels duty to proceed againſt <hi>Theudas</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> in caſe it was demonſtrated unto them their doctrines were erroneous (notwithſtanding <hi>Gamaliels</hi> advice to the contrary) cannot I conceive be rationally anſwered, except there had been a certain knowledge of the nature of thoſe errours, and upon ſuppoſition that thoſe errors were groſſe and dangerous, as it is like they were, even unto inſurrection and ſedition, I anſwer, that they ought not to have hearkened unto his advice, but to have proceeded according to rules of juſtice made in that behalf; and it is not denyed, but that the Chriſtian Magiſtrate hath a coercive power in matters of Religion, in things that are of a morall and capitall conſideration, ſuch as are prophane ſwearings, curſings, blaſphemies, and ſuch things; that firſt are againſt the light of nature and conſcience; yea, ſecondly, of curſed apoſtaſie from Chriſt, profeſſedly denying him to be God, or come in the fleſh, or wickedly blaſpheming him, teaching men ſo; and thirdly, ſuch as are turbulent, violent, mutinous and factious in raiſing up par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the diſturbance of the peace of the State, as the late Biſhops did; Neither hath M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> in my beſt obſervation, ſaid or writ any thing to the contrary in his <hi>Theomachia,</hi> or elſewhere; for I cannot ſee any ſuch thing in any of his doctrines raiſed from his Text of that Sermon; and the main point which he proſecuted, and which was (as it were) the ſpirit and life of all thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar inſtructions therein contained, was, that, <hi>For any man to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or attempt the ſuppreſſion of any</hi> Doctrine, Practice <hi>or</hi> Way, <hi>that is from God, is to fight againſt God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This point is proved, and cleered and confeſt on all hands to be a truth of God, and if you look into application, he renders thoſe obnoxious to the wrath of God, who ſhall exerciſe <hi>any high handed appoſition or conteſtation againſt any</hi> Way, Doctrine <hi>or</hi> Practice <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTIL they have proof upon proof, demonſtration upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113141:16"/>evidence upon evidence; yea, all the ſecurity that men in any ordinary way (at leaſt) can have, that ſuch</hi> Wayes <hi>or</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines <hi>only pretend God to be the author of them, and that in truth they are not at all from him, but either from man or of a baſer parentage.</hi> What is this againſt the juſt power of a Magiſtrate in matters of Religion, and no more power then this can you prove, even from the example of the kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> and therefore, if you will reduce the Chriſtian Kings and Magiſtrates unto them as a pattern and example of their power in things ſpirituall, and make the caſe directly as it is, you muſt bring in ſome inſtance or other of a difference between the holy and godly Prophets and people of God themſelves, and that in a caſe very difficult and intricate, and hard to be found out from the Scriptures or any of thoſe wayes wherein God did uſually reveale his minde, and that in ſuch a caſe the magiſtrate did determine the buſineſſe according to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and compell the diſſenting party to ſubmiſſion thereunto, and that according to the approbation of God; and therefore an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for Magiſtrates under the Goſpel: ſuch is the very caſe in hand, as might be evidently declared. Moreover, there were thoſe that did differ in many things of a very deep and ſerious conſideration (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they made profeſſion of the Jewiſh Religion and government they were tolerated) as is very cleer (as I ſaid before;) <hi>Sadduces, Phariſees,</hi> and ſeverall other ſorts were permitted; neither do I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member where they were compelled againſt their judgements, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in matter of Profeſſion or Practice, except (as being members of that Church) to the main doctrines, worſhip and government expreſſed in the Word; and ſurely there is far more, and better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the toleration and permiſſion of the Independent, then can be given for the toleration of ſuch perſons as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, for theſe agree with Presbyterians in the main grounds of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and principles of the Goſpel; theſe are confeſt by their Brethren to be holy, godly and learned, and of ſingular uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, both in Church and Commonwealth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of none others are pleaded for in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Goodwins Theomachia,</hi> from that Sermon which you mention. But wee will not ſtand on this particular, becauſe it may be one of the corruptions of thoſe times, to ſuffer ſuch Sects, eſpecially the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> who though (for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) not reproved by our Saviour, as ſome other corruptions were
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113141:16"/>not mentioned by him. Wee have ſaid enough before to this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: As for thoſe Doctrines which you ſay you would raiſe from that Text, if you were to preach upon it, I conceive the two firſt you mention are indeed very naturall, but how you will draw the third from thence as naturall from that Text I cannot ſee; but it would be a digreſſion for mee to meddle with that, and therefore I leave it to your own further conſideration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUMENT IX.</head>
               <p>I Deſire to know whether that law, <hi>Deut. 13.</hi> of putting a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to death, or any one that ſhould entice men from the Way of the true God, there be not morall equity in it, and therefore binde the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and Chuches of God to the end of the world? <hi>Calvin</hi> and the Church vf <hi>Geneva</hi> burnt a blaſphemer, they looked upon the morall equity of that law, <hi>Levit. 24.16.</hi> He that blaſphemeth the name of the Lord ſhall ſurely be put to death, all the Congregation ſhall ſtone him; Why ſhould not Chriſtians be as tender of the name of God as the <hi>Jewes</hi> were? Is not his name as great and glorious, that it may be more ſecurely blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed now then it might then? But a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> preſident will have but little authority with <hi>Congregationall</hi> Churches, therefore I deſire that <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Cotton</hi> (one of your own, upon whoſe learning and judgement the wel-willer to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Prynne</hi> (hee that put forth the firſt anſwer to his twelve Queries) would have men much to rely) may be heard ſpeak in the point, in his book, entituled <hi>Powring out the ſeven Vials,</hi> on <hi>Rev. 16.4, 5, 6, 7. Verſes.</hi> His very doctrine is this; <hi>Upon the diſcovery of the deadly corruption of the Sea of</hi> Rome, it was a righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and ſuch as argued him unchangeable, ever like himſelfe, that the Prieſts and Jeſuits, who carryed that Religion up and down the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhould be adjudged or condemned to a bloody death. His meaning is evidently this, <hi>not becauſe enemies to the civill State, but becauſe they carryed Ordinances, Doctrines up and down the world which were no better then the blood of a dead man, and every ſoule that drank of them died, therefore they themſelves muſt drink blood.</hi> Within a few lines after his doctrine, he quotes <hi>Zach. 13.2, 3.</hi> (ſpealing of the times under the Goſpel, 'tis cleer from the firſt verſe, and ſo doth <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomas Goodwin</hi> interpret it in his <hi>triall of the growth of Grace</hi>) God will out off the falſe Prophet, and if any falſe Prophet ſhall ariſe, his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113141:17"/>Father and Mother ſhall thruſt him therow, becauſe hee ſpeaks lies in the name of the God of truth, be ſhall not live. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which Text, hee thus gloſſes, <hi>It is not ſpoken of his typicall death</hi> (i) <hi>of his death by Church-cenſure or baniſhment, which have a kinde of death in them, but of ſuch a death as that he was not worthy to live, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he caſt a lie upon the God of Truth, the Oracle of Truth.</hi> In his firſt Reaſons of his point he affirms, that no Magiſtrate ought to have put <hi>Paul</hi> to death for his errours and blaſphemies, becauſe be did all ignorantly, <hi>1 Tim. 1.14.</hi> had the truth been made known to him, hee would not have done as hee did, but ſuch as blaſpheme and teach errours wilfully after admonition twice or thrice, the glorious light of the Goſpel ſhining round about them, thoſe hee affirms, ought to be looked upon with another eye, ought to drink blood.</p>
               <p>His firſt objection is this, <hi>In the new Teſtament we muſt look for a ſpirituall death</hi> (i) <hi>Church-cenſure only:</hi> He anſwers, <hi>his Text is in the new Teſtament, not in the old,</hi> the new Teſtament ſayes ſuch are worthy to drink the blood of their own hearts; the holy Ghoſt ſayes, hee will have it true according to the Letter; and further anſwers, that 'twas one of <hi>Moſes</hi> his morall lawes of perpetuall equity, thruſting men away from God is as odious now as then.</p>
               <p>In his fifth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe he has theſe very words, <hi>Hereſie is no more pleaſing to him, nor blaſphemie, nor ſeducing, nor to change the Way of Gods worſhip, and to draw men to Wayes wherein they cannot enjoy God in peace;</hi> murther of ſoules is no more welcome to God now then of old, and therefore if there were a law to puniſh ſuch with capitall puniſhment, it is a like juſtice in God to enjoyn ſuch lawes in every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>His ſecond Objection is this, <hi>Conſcience muſt not be forced, men muſt not be put to death for their conſcience.</hi> Hee anſwers, <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques were as conſcionable in the old Teſtament as now;</hi> and if any man have a conſcience to turn men from God, God would have men have as much conſcience to cut them off; gloſſing upon <hi>Tit. 3. 10, 11.</hi> thus: <hi>He that will not be admoniſhed is rejected, given up to the civil Magiſtrate to be puniſhed, or put to death, not for his conſcience, but becauſe hee ſins againſt his conſcience, the cleere ſhining light of the Goſpel.</hi> Whereupon I thinke it followes, that any errour whatſoever, though not fundamentall, if it be wilfully held and taught againſt inſtructions and admonitions, eſpecially if it make Sects
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113141:17"/>and Factions, let them be never ſo conſcionable in their Wayes, profeſſe never ſo much of God to be in them, the Magiſtrate may and ought to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them according to the nature of their errours, and their mouths muſt be ſtopped, that their teaching do no more ſubvert.</p>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, if that law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. of putting a falſe Prophet to death, or any one that ſhall entice men from the true God be morall equity, and ſtill binding the Magiſtrates and Churches of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of the world, is to be underſtood (as it there followes) of inducing to Idolatry, wherein notwithſtanding there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing peculiar to that nation, as in the 15<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h verſe of that Chapter, <hi>If a City ſhould turn away from the true God, to ſerve other gods, that they ſhauld ſmite the inhabitants thereof, and the cattle thereof with the edge of the ſword, and that they ſhould gather all the ſpoyle thereof into the midſt of the ſtreets thereof, and ſhould burn with fire the city, and all the ſpoyle thereof every whit, and that it ſhould be an heap for ever, and that it ſhould be never built again,</hi> verſ. 16. But this, becauſe it is circumſtantiall, I will not inſiſt upon. Now how far the morall equity of this law may extend in other caſes, I will not now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute; becauſe whether it reach further or not, no way concernes the law fulneſſe of Congregationall Churches.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as for your inſtancing <hi>Calvin,</hi> and the Churches of <hi>Geneva's</hi> burning a blaſphemer, and grounding their act upon the morall equity of that law, ſpoken of <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.16. I ſhall ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but referre you to what <hi>Calvin</hi> hath written of it, a Tract entituled <hi>Explicatio perfidiae Valentin Gentilis,</hi> and to Gods <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of it one day in the ſight of heaven and earth, it is notoriouſly evident to be meant of a prophane, wilfull, wicked blaſphemer and curſer of God; if that Heretique were ſuch, as <hi>Galvin</hi> ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſhew, <hi>Explicat perfidiae Valent. Gentil,</hi> hee is condemned in the very Text; but it is not meant of one that <hi>through ignorance</hi> miſconceiveth <hi>of God,</hi> either in reſpect of his <hi>Attributes,</hi> or in reſpect of the <hi>Trinity;</hi> and ſurely, if ſuch kinde of miſtakings ſhould not be atoned but by ſuch ſacrifices, we ſhould have hot work amongſt Chriſtians; yea, and with ſuch ſacrifices God would be pleaſed after the manner as he would be pleaſed with the ſacrificing of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113141:18"/>fruit of our body for the ſin of our ſouls; yea, for any thing that I know, and they that ſhal deal ſo with men for ſuch miſtakes in ſuch things (I think) are in a great error, as well as the miſtaken them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and my reaſon is, becauſe men have been in many places but meanly inſtructed and educated in the right underſtanding therof, but oftentimes notions of the deepeſt cognizance are handed over unto men from father to father, in a traditionall manner, without a cleer debating, evincing and confirming the truth thereof, and libertie given to declare ones doubts herein; inſomuch, that meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a deceiver, many are ſo ſoon led away with his errour, which is one great cauſe of the ſo many wofull diviſions, and errors that are now amongſt us, and (by the way) this indeed would be a buſineſſe worthy the endeavours of our godly and learned men of our age, to take pains in buſineſſes of this nature) <hi>viz.</hi> the great things of the Law and Goſpel of God, to eſtabliſh men in the right underſtanding of the grounds of their Religion, to the rectifying of their judgements, and the reformation of their lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and not thus unhappily alwayes to wrangle about things of more inferiour conſideration.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, ſuppoſe that Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. and that alſo <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.16. be morall? what is this to the buſineſſe in hand? M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Goodwin</hi> in his <hi>Theomachia,</hi> nor elſewhere (that I know of) did ever plead for the toleration, either of ſuch a falſe Prophet ſpoken of, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. or ſuch a blaſphemer ſpoken of, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.16. And your ſelf brings in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Cotton,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Goodwin,</hi> (men of the ſame Way and opinion with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> in matters of Church-government) to clear the Independent party from any ſuch opinion, which (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding) is inſinuated into mens thoughts to be their darling, when, alas, it is nothing ſo; and therefore why are they charged herewith? Surely want of love in the accuſers, and not guilt in the accuſed, is the ground of their accuſation; But the Queſtion is about the Magiſtrates compelling men, even in matters of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and hard finding out the minde of God therein, and which indeed oftentimes, is out of the cognizance and cleer knowledge of the very Magiſtrate himſelf. But can this follow, the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a falſe Prophet that turneth away people from the Lord to be put to death? <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. Will it therefore follow, that that Prophet that ſhall teach any thing at all contrary to the ſuppoſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113141:18"/>and diſputable minde of God, that he alſo muſt be dealt withall after ſuch a manner? is there not great difference between mens pleading for this and that kinde of government of the Churches of Chriſt, and the turning away men from the faith of Chriſt? do you not all confeſſe, that the Independent men are holy, godly, learned men; and uſefull unto the begetting unto, and building men up in the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt? and doth not God ſeal unto their Miniſtry as well as unto any others Miniſtry? And ſo for the other Text, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.16. A blaſphemer muſt be ſtoned to death; will it therefore follow, that an Independent muſt not be ſuffered to live in a Chriſtian Commonwealth? ſurely this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion never grew on that Scripture, nor in any other that I have yet ſeen.</p>
                  <p>You ſay, <hi>That any errour, though not fundamentall, if it be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully held, and taught againſt inſtructions and admonitions, eſpecially if it make</hi> Sects <hi>and</hi> Factions, <hi>let them be never ſo conſcionable in their Way, profeſſe never ſo much of God in them, the Magiſtrate may, and ought to puniſh them according to nature of their errours,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is not ſufficient a point be cleared, but that it be cleared to the perſons wee would perſwade; elſe they are to be born with till that be done, as appeares in the weaker <hi>Jewes</hi> about ceremonies, and ſome of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> about the reſurrection.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is confeſt, that obſtinacy and wilfulneſſe, and that after inſtructions &amp; admonitions, is juſtly puniſhable by the Magiſtrate, where ever it be found; but, <hi>Quid inde?</hi> where will you faſten this <hi>obſtinacie</hi> and <hi>wilfulneſſe,</hi> that you may bring your ſuppoſition to the buſineſſe in hand? upon the Independent? May they not as well recharge it upon them from whence it came? have there not been inſtructions and admonitions on both fides? and is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction as far off from many godly and learned men it the one as in the other? Muſt <hi>nomen multitudinis</hi> determine the buſineſſe? No, certainly, your ſelf hath propoſed a better rule, and that is, <hi>the making of Sects and Factions;</hi> and for this, quit you the one party, the other quits it ſelf: As, firſt, for <hi>the making of Sects:</hi> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is not the triall of doctrines before received, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of doctrines (if compelled by authority) before the triall thereof that makes Sects, it is not the mutuall binding of men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the bond of love, and the mutuall ingagements unto
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113141:19"/>watch fulneſſe, inſtructions, exhortations one unto another (which the Apoſtle preſcribes, as means againſt mens being toſſed up and down by every wind of doctrine, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14.15, 16.) it is not theſe things I ſay, that makes Sects, but the want of theſe things; it is true, there are ſeverall Sects that profeſſe theſe Wayes, ſo there are ſeverall Sects that profeſſe the Goſpell and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, in ſo much, that Father ſaid, <hi>The Devill was let looſe, when hee ſaw the Saints that ſprung up under his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> is the Goſpell or Proteſtant Religion the worſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? An <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as for the other part of your rule of triall <hi>(the making of Factions,)</hi> let the Magiſtrate ſpare none where it is found, no, upon his perill, and as he will anſwer it before the Lord, let him not ſpare any; for this indeed is the main end of his authority, to keep the people committed unto him in peace, and to be a nurſing father unto the Church, if any be in his dominion: but who are theſe <hi>Faction-makers?</hi> ſurely not the meek in the earth, the weapons of whoſe warfare are arguments, reaſons and Scripture, and who would have men be at peace with all men, not men that are gentle, ſofe, ſtriving only with the cords of a man <hi>(viz.)</hi> reaſon and underſtanding, and not with the whips of Horſes, and the goads of Oxen. Were not the Biſhops a factious gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? And wherein did it appeare? was it not by their inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations into the Magiſtracie, to have their Wayes maintained, urged and preſt upon men by a law, by fines, impriſonments, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, whips and pillories, by procuring Lawes, and Canons, Decrees and Injunctions, to preſſe men againſt the truth, their judgements and conſciences unto obedience thereof? and hath not this State-troubling generation, raiſed up and kindled that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire, that is like now to devour the kingdome? Well, if this evill ſpirit of diſtraction, contention and faction be found in the Congregationall party, let not the eye of the Magiſtrate ſpare them, but let him take heed, that he do not <hi>condemne the innocent, and juſtifie the guilty.</hi> Now the Lord in mercy conjure that ſpirit of Faction where ever it be found, and give the Magiſtracie of this poor kingdome wiſdome to obſerve where it is, and prevent all dangers thereby, that this diſtreſſed Nation may flouriſh in truth and peace.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113141:19"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the Arguments or doubts that for the preſent I deſire ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in, that my judgement and conſcience may be ſettled; Let it not be thought that I am making a party againſt them; or that I think my Arguments cannot be anſwered, I am better perſwaded of their holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and abilities then to think they will take up any opinions, but they can ſatisfie any equall minded man that asks them a reaſon of ſuch their faith; nor yet let it be thought that I have followed theſe objections with a ſpirit that intends not to receive ſatisfaction; I call him to witneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe Tribunall I and all the purpoſes of my heart muſt ſtand naked one day for to be judged, my very heart (if I underſtand mine own heart) ſtands open to receive all the truths of God, whoever brings them, with what externall inconveniences ſoever they come accompanied, I have ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my doubts, it may be thought, with ſomewhat too much earneſtneſſe and heat, I am ſure with all ſingleneſſe of heart, aiming at nothing but to know more of the mind and Way of God, that God may be more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in me. Grace be with us all.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your true friend to love and ſerve you and yours in Chriſt Jeſus, &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <head>REPLY.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the Anſwers which for the preſent I humbly return unto your Arguments, which (I muſt confeſſe again) have been tendered with more ſweetneſſe and candidneſſe of language, phraſe, and expreſſion, then ever yet I did reade any arguments of this nature before, wherein, if I have ſhewed, that which is indeed. mine own, <hi>viz.</hi> weakneſſes, inſufficiencies and miſtakes, I hope the power of Chriſt in you (<hi>viz.</hi> the ſpirit of love) will cover them all; and here again I muſt renue my former requeſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the letting ſlip, if any thing be weake, and your more ſerious thoughts upon that which is more valid and conſiderable; to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113141:20"/>preſume your ſatisfaction, would be too great ambition, though to aſſure my ſelf of your acceptation is my perfect confidence; Sir, I leave what I have here tendered, unto your prudent conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, deſiring the Almighty to leade us all into the wayes of truth and peace, knitting our hearts together in love, and ſo guiding us by his counſels to bring us to his glory, which is the hearty prayers, Sir,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Of yours in all Chriſtian love and ſincerity, J. P.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:113141:20"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
